Guide to the Grimes Family Films and Other Materials AIA.040
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grimes Family Films and Other Materials
1896-2005
1947-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grimes, Paddy, 1890-1978
Grimes, Claire
Grimes, John
AIA.040
2.19 Linear Feet in 1 letter sized manuscript box, 1 half legal sized manuscript box, 1 record carton, and 1 shared legal sized manuscript box
14 film reels in 13 8mm film cans and 1 16mm film can
2 videocassettes (betacamsp) in 2 Sony Betacam SP tapes
2 reel in 2 microfilm reels
7 sound tape reels in 7 quarter inch audio reels
The Grimes Family is an Irish American family based in the greater New York City area perhaps best known for their ownership of the Irish Echo newspaper from 1955 until 2011. Through its domestic and international social, political, sporting, and entertainment coverage, the Irish Echo served as a channel of communication and source of documentation for the Irish American community. This collection consists of home movies, photographs, publications, ephemera, and other materials created and collected by members of the Grimes Family, including Paddy, John, and Claire. The majority of the collection is comprised of some of the Grimes' home movies, documenting family life as well as various Irish American social functions in the greater New York City area during the 1950s. Some of the more prominent subjects of these films include sporting events, St. Patrick's Day parades, United Irish Counties Association Feiseanna at Fordham University, and the Irish Echo.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Echo Photographs (AIA 045)
Archives of Irish American United Irish Counties Association Collection (AIA 056)
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
The Grimes Family is an Irish American family based in the greater New York City area perhaps best known for their ownership of the Irish Echo newspaper from 1955 until 2011. Patrick J. (Paddy) Grimes, a native of County Offaly, purchased the newspaper in 1955 in an attempt to promote the family's travel agency, Grimes Travel Agency. Through its domestic and international social, political, sporting, and entertainment coverage, the Irish Echo served as a channel of communication and source of documentation for the Irish American community. For example, the paper produced brochures and journals for the various county societies and other social organizations in the 1950s and 1960s. Following Paddy's death in 1978, his son John became the paper's editor and publisher until his death in 1987, after which his wife Claire assumed the roles.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of home movies, photographs, publications, ephemera, and other materials created and collected by members of the Grimes Family, including Paddy, John, and Claire. The majority of the collection is comprised of some of the Grimes' home movies, documenting family life as well as various Irish American social functions in the greater New York City area during the 1950s. Some of the more prominent subjects of these films include sporting events, St. Patrick's Day parades, and United Irish Counties Association Feiseanna at Fordham University. The collection also includes photographs and documents focusing on the Irish Echo newspaper.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Prcoedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Films were donated by Claire Grimes in the late 1990s. The accession number associated with this gift is 1997.041. The remainder of the collection was donated by Claire Grimes several years later.
Amateur films; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Irish echo (New York, N.Y.); Photographs.; Audiovisual materials.; Correspondence.; Articles.; United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.
- P.J. Kerley and Family Leaving for Ireland at Idlewild Airport, 1957; cuid14047 (Film COMP aia40-a)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1956; cuid14048 (Film COMP aia40-d)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, 1953; cuid14049 (Film COMP aia40-g)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, Speaking Platforms, 1953; cuid14050 (Film COMP aia40-i)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade and United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1955; cuid14051 (Film COMP aia40-o)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade and Sir Basil Brooke Protest at Idlewild Airport, 1950; cuid14052 (Film COMP aia40-r)
- Ireland and New York Compilation Reel, circa 1950-1959; cuid14053; 1 film reels 16mm; 2 videocassettes (betacamsp) Transfers of 16mm film (Box 3, 16mm film reels AIA40-2, Box Shared Tamiment 088, Betacam sp AIA40-Grimes 1 (31142046752690), Betacam sp AIA40-Grimes 2 (31142046752708), Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.40_cuid14053)
- Gaelic Teams Disembarking Shannon Airport, Ireland, circa 1954; cuid84 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-j)
- Dublin, Ireland, 1955; cuid85 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-u)
- Dublin, Ireland, 1955; cuid86 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-v)
- Dublin, Ireland (Probably "Flight of the Gaels"), circa 1955; cuid87 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-m)
- Paddy Casey Leaving for Ireland at Idlewild Airport, 1958; cuid88 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-b)
- Wedding and Gaelic Football Team, circa 1965; cuid89 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-n)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1956; cuid90 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-c)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1956 March; cuid91 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-e)
- Pat Grimes Graduation and United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, 1952; cuid92 (Item aia40-f, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid92)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University; Dublin, Ireland, 1952; cuid93 (Item aia40-k, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid93)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University (Includes Football Match), 1952; cuid94 (Item aia40-l, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid94)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1955; cuid95 (Item aia40-h, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid95)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1955; cuid96 (Item aia40-t, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid96)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1950-1959; cuid97 (Item aia40-q, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid97)
- P.J. Grimes Film, circa 1955; cuid98 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-s)
- Indian Couple Visits Country House, circa 1953; cuid99 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-p)
- American Football Newsreel, circa 1947; cuid100 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-y)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, circa 1950-1959; cuid101 (Box 3, 8mm film reel AIA40-w)
- Air Lingus Music Bed 60 Sec Radio Produced by: HHCC, undated (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0001)
- A Letter from Ireland, Aer Lingus, undated (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0002)
- Untitled, undated (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0003)
- Clancy Brothers, undated (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0004)
- Untitled, undated (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0005)
- Various Songs, 1960 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0006)
  Scope and Contents
  Music from Perry Como, Father Sydney MacEwan, The Four Lads, The King and I, Al Jolson, South Pacific, Straus Waltzes, Nelson Eddie Sings, and Sounds in Space featured on this audio reel.
- Various Songs, undated (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 40.0007)
- Europe Greece 1928.6 thru 1940.2, Reel 7 of 7, 1928-1940 (Box 1, Reel 40.0008)
- Europe Greece 1961.5 thru 1961.11, Reel 2 of 3 (Box 1, Reel 40.0009)
- Aer Lingus 1980 TV campaign "Britain vs. Ireland" "Europe vs. Ireland" (Box 1, 8mm film reel 40.0010)
- Irish Echo, 1928-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Drumgoole, 1989, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Grimes Family, 1987, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Paddy Grimes, 1957-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Emerald Fund, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- The Irish Echo: the First 70 Years, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- B/W Photostat of Irish Echo Offices, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence - S.R. Slavern, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)